Guide to the Thomas Stamm Papers TAM.081
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Thomas Stamm Papers
1934-1979, undated
TAM.081
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
1.0 linear feet in 1 record box
Thomas Stamm [d. 198?] was a U.S. Trotskyist (and homosexual) and one-time member of the Political Committee of the Workers Party who, along with Hugo Oehler, founded the Revolutionary Workers League. This small collection consists of one record box of material generated and collected by Thomas Stamm during the course of his personal research, writing, and involvement with the Revolutionary Workers League.
Stamm, Thomas.
Box 1
Historical/Biographical Note
Thomas Stamm [d. 198?] was a U.S. Trotskyist (and homosexual) and one-time member of the Political Committee of the Workers Party who opposed the Party's 1935 decision to attempt to enter the Socialist Party of the United States in an attempt to broaden its influence. With Hugo Oehler, he formed the Revolutionary Workers League (RWL). In 1937, the group renounced Trotskyism, but while Oehler concluded that Trotsky had split with Marxism in 1934, Stamm held that Trotsky had degenerated in 1928, and the two split. Oehler retained the majority of the group, but Stamm set up a rival organization of the same name. This was some times known as RWL Revolt after its periodical, which ran Vol. I #1 March 26 1938 to Vol II #14 January 7, 1940.
According to "Problems in History & Theory: The End of 'American Trotskyism'?" Part 2 by Alan Wald, there are currently no studies of gay and lesbian Trotskyists in existence. Thomas Stamm, a gay Trotskyist leader, was interviewed only by Robert Alexander.
Arrangement
The order in which these materials were sent to the Tamiment Library has been maintained.
Appraisal note
No materials were separated from this collection.
Scope and Content Note
This small collection consists of one record box of material generated and collected by Thomas Stamm during the course of his personal research, writing, and involvement with the Revolutionary Workers League. The majority of the collection consists of correspondence between Thomas Stamm and other individuals such as Max Schachtman, Carl Cowl, James T. Farrell, Meyer Shapiro, Robert J. Alexander and Edward Oehler. Copies of publications such as Fighting Worker, Ahora, Political Notes, and the Marxist Worker are interspersed throughout the collection. There are four folders (53-56) that pertain specifically to Stamm's interest in the Trotsky assassination, although this topic may be present in other areas of the collection. There are 4 unidentified tapes on magnetic reels labeled 1-4 and accompanied by a typed transcript of a "tape 2" which may be the tape 2 that is present in this collection. Personal material related to Thomas Stamm exists in the form of his diary at the start of the collection. There are also many published and unpublished manuscripts and articles by Thomas Stamm, some of which are undated, although a possible date range could be ascertained by examining surrounding and related material in the collection.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Researchers interested in using audiovisual materials in this collection (films, cassette tapes, VHS tapes, et cetera) must use a digitized copy, which we refer to as an access copy. Researchers may view an item’s original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that already have already been digitized are noted in the collection’s finding aid and can be requested in our reading room; materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. These requests are free of charge and can be made in anticipation of your visit. The process typically takes four to six weeks. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@library.nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A librarian will respond to you with further information.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
These materials were donated by May Stamm in 1980. The accession number associated with this donation is 1980.013.
Oehler, Hugo.; Revolutionary Workers League of the U.S.; Stamm, May; Stamm, Thomas.; Socialism and homosexuality.; Trotskyism |z United States.; Trotskyist parties |z United States.; Trotskyists |z United States.
- Thomas Stamm diary, Jan 18, 1949-Mar 21, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1945-1947 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence and notes, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1942-1950 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence with Carl Cowl, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Letter from Irving to Tom, Sep 26, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence with Hank Ross (Marsh), 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence with Max Shachtman, James T. Farrell, Meyer Shpairo, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence with John Poulos re: William Krehm and Louis Basky, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Letters from Jackson Mayers (Drake) from Europe, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Letter to Thomas Stamm from Robert J. Alexander, Feb 22, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence with Robert Pitcoff, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence with Florence [Hazel Korn], 1972 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Thomas Stamm and others correspondence with Edward Oler [Oehler], 1972-1978 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Letter to George Novack and Atrocious History manuscript, Dec 3, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Correspondence with Barbara West (SWP archivist) and letter from Jack Barnes (SWP National Secretary) to Tamiment, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Correspondence re: labor encyclopedia, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Correspondence re: communists in the book publishing field, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Correspondence with Esquire and Where is Your Lantern Dwight MacDonald? manuscript, Mar 27, 1965-Oct 4, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Letter to Marxist Worker, Sep 26, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Pathfinder press letter to Thomas Stamm, Mar 14, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Correspondence with U.S. General Services Administration re: Warren Commission transcripts, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Thomas Stamm memorial speech to Lou Bobroff, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Italy is Desperately Hungry by Jack Armor and Thomas Stamm, clipping of article by Olive Karen and other manuscripts, 1946, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Manuscript on Stalinism [author unknown], undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
- "Who Wrote Stalin's Book" by Thomas Stamm, submitted to New Yorker, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Articles for encyclopedia, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Notes and unfinished miscellaneous material, 1940, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Excerpt from letter Louis Breier to Munsey Gleaton, re: AWP-CLA forthcoming merger, Oct 30, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Los Angeles Conference on Revolutionary Regroupment, Jul 1977 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Letter to Larry Lawson, Spartacist League on situation in RWL; The Logic of Ideas, 1936-1937, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Data on unions, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Material re: Ed Welsh, 1942, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Excerpts from a letter on workers control of production, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Notes on Fifth Convention of RWL; Minutes of final conference RWL, Jan 18-19, 1941, May 30, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- 1946 negotiations with RWL material (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Fighting Worker, clippings on unity, "Four Elements," "Origins", 1945, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- State Labor Relations Board case: Thomas Stamm v. Sinram Brothers, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Research report on the irreconciliability of captialism and communism and supplemental research material, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- "Report by Your Organizer," Sid Lens, Jan 5, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Unpublished article written for Detroit suburban newspaper by McGruff?, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
- The Jewish Labor Committee [historical paper on the organization], undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
- "One Small Step Forward" statement by Jim and Grace Lee Boggs and Freddie and Lyman Paine, undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Financial standing of Budd Co., war years profits, 1936-1939, 1941-1944 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Political Notes vol. 1 no.3, Aug 6, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Detroit Newsletter, undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Schematic outline of chapter 2 of "The Thesis Argument: by Joseph L. Morse, undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
- The Four Elements, undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
- The Democratic Manifesto (5 copies), undated (Box 1, Folder 50)
- 4 tapes [untitled], undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Transcript of tape 2 [possibly from tape 2 in Folder 51], undated (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Material on Healy's accusations against Novak and Hanson regarding Trotsky assassination, 1972-1977 (Box 1, Folder 53)
- Copy from Ahora issue #465 re: Siqueiro's involvement in Trotsky assassination attempt, undated (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Correspondence re: Trotsky assassination, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 55-56)
- Miscellaneous leaflets, brochures, xerox copies and notes, 1945, undated (Box 1, Folder 57)
- Clippings, 1937, 1941, 1951, 1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 58)
- Paris Commune post cards, undated (Box 1, Folder 59)